Can’t you be careful?
Are you injured?
No but my bike has been damaged.
It is okay, I have an insurance.
Insurance? Show me the papers.
Here bro!
It’s only for the third party and not own damage.
This can’t be claimed.
What? I know nothing of this bro.
Ok I will tell. Want to listen?
Ok but shall we sit and talk?
Yes! You sit, I will get some water for you.
We will buy a vehicle with insurance.
Let it be car or bike.
There are two things- own damage & third party.
Own damage is not affecting anybody else but you alone getting injured or
your bike getting damaged.
This is own damage.
You can claim insurance for this.
If it was an accident with another vehicle,
They would be affected.
So you can use this third party insurance policy in your insurance
and claim it for them too from the insurance company.
If you are going on your vehicle and another person hits you with his vehicle
You can claim insurance from the third party policy through the other person for your damaged vehicle.
This is the difference between own damage and third party policy.
Your insurance policy has not been renewed for own damage
But third party insurance is still valid for 3 years.
That is why I told that you can’t claim for your bike.
What bro? When I bought this bike, they said the insurance is for 5 years.
Yes but it is for third party insurance. In that you still have 3 more years.
Own damage is only for one year and you haven’t renewed it.
Bad time!
If I had renewed it, I could have claimed for my injuries too right?
No! Own damage is only for the vehicle and not for you.
If you need it for yourself, you should have applied a Personal Accident Policy.
Personal Accident Policy is mandatory from January 1st, 2019
for all new vehicles along with other insurance.
And for people who have bought before that,
It is better to contact their insurance company and get a Personal Accident Policy.
We can check whether we have applied for a Personal Accident Policy
or not by seeing our insurance papers.
The vehicle owner can cover up to 15 lakhs.
If your vehicle is used for any of your family member,
You can apply a Personal Accident Policy in their name.
If your friends too use the same vehicle,
You can get a Personal Accident Policy ‘unnamed’.
You can claim the insurance according to the injuries caused.
Oh!
But for third party insurance, it is both for the person and the vehicle.
All this is regulated by IRDAI.
They are the ones who fix the amount to be claimed for third party insurance.
You can see in your insurance paper which has third party and OD.
Oh! So own damage is only for the vehicle.
If it is for us, we should get a PA policy.
If it is for a third party insurance, it covers both for the person and the vehicle. Right?
Yes! You have understood it very well.
Now, see your insurance paper and tell me the details.
It says Package policy- OD and third party insurance.
Also, I have a PA policy too.
You should have bought it after January 1st, 2019.
How many years is it for OD and third party insurance?
According to September 1st, 2018, third party insurance rules had been changed.
For a car, third party insurance is compulsory for 3 years.
For a bike, third party insurance is compulsory for 5 years.
OD is for one year, minimum.
Later you can renew it.
It is not compulsory that you should get an insurance
in the same showroom where you buy your vehicle.
No one should compel you too.
We must know this.
What are the situations applicable for this insurance?
It’s applicable for fire accidents, theft, damaged in any riots,
Damage by natural disasters and terrorist attacks.
Most importantly you can claim it for accidents.
Oh! When is it not applicable?
Not applicable.
Accident caused while driving without a license or drunk can’t be claimed.
And accidents caused due to brake failures can’t be claimed too.
Accidents caused while using your vehicles for any illegal activities can’t be claimed.
So, if your vehicle is stolen, you should file a case immediately or you'll be in trouble.
Yes that’s right!
What is Insured’s Declared Value –Rs.36,000?
How do they calculate it?
They would look at the vehicle’s condition, year, model and type and fix the rate for a year.
This is IDV.
You haven’t renewed your OD yet.
If you are going to renew it now and you haven’t claimed anything this year,
You might get a discount of 20-50%.
This is called No Claim Bonus. (NCB)
Next time when you go for renewal,
check for NCB, PA policy.
Right! I will see hereafter.
Now my bike is damaged.
How do I claim it?
For that, you should have renewed it.
Yes I know. If it was renewed how would I claim it?
Then, take a picture of the injuries and damages caused to you and your vehicle.
Send it to your insurance company.
They will see it.
If the damage is minimal, you can leave it in the workshop and claim the money.
If the damage is severe,
they would send a surveyor to check after you send the pictures.
The surveyor would check on the damage and note it.
You can then get the vehicle repaired in a workshop or showroom.
If you have a cashless service in your insurance,
You need not pay.
The money will be directly given to the workshop or showroom.
So, it is important to see whether you have a cashless service while getting an insurance.
This is how you should claim it.
-Oh is it?
-Yes!
If someone else hits me, how do I claim?
You should get the insurance policy details from the other person.
Then you must inform your insurance company and the police.
They will take care of it.
Now, if my third party insurance expires and I hit someone.
How will the other person claim it?
In critical situations like this,
They would get the desired amount from you.
They would claim the third party insurance which was paid earlier and give it to the affected.
You don’t be without renewing.
Then you can’t even claim for OD.
Yes I should renew it.
Don’t forget all this.
Tell all the points that we discussed now to everyone.
Young people should definitely know it because
the accidents taking place are worse.
Getting these policies are good.
It is not our fault not to know this because no one taught us.
This week is Road Safety Week.
Wearing helmet on seeing the police is not road safety.
Getting insurance, saving ourselves and others is good.
So, renew your papers soon. Ok?
Yes sure!
Now only I understood well about insurance.
I will share it with others.
Shall I come with you to drop you?
No I am alright bro.
-Use your helmet.
-Ok bro!
Right!